Well, that's all for today.
（桜井(さくらい)先生）はい　じゃあ
今日は これで終わりです
The days are getting shorter,
日が短くなってきたので―
so please try to be home before it gets dark.
暗くなる前に
帰るようにしてくださいね
（片品(かたしな)）よーし 遊ぶぞ 遊ぶぞ
（千代田(ちよだ)）何して遊ぼっか
（中之条 剛(なかのじょうつよし)）何でも すぐ
プラズマって言っちゃうのもね
（相生祐子(あいおいゆうこ)）
♪ フンフン フッフフン
Nano-chan!
（祐子）なーのちゃん
（東雲(しののめ)なの）は… はいっ
Yes?!
Let's go home together.
一緒に帰ろうよ
駅前のアレ 食べてかない
Do you want to stop by that place near the station?
Eh?
ねっ どう？
What do you think?
えっ えっと ああっ
Um... Uh...
Hey, Mio-chan. Do you want to come, to-
ねえ みおちゃんも一緒にって…
Huh?
あれ？ もう帰っちゃったのかなあ
Did she leave already?
じゃ なの… あっ あれ？
Then, Nano-
Huh?
ああ 黙って出てきちゃった
相生さんに悪いことしちゃったかな
I ended up running away.
That wasn't very nice to Aioi-san.
If only I could've introduced myself more like a normal girl...
もうちょっと普通の女の子みたいに
あいさつできてればなあ
（なの）
しし… 東雲なのって いいます
My name is Shinonome Nano!
え… えっと
それでですね あのっ
And you see, this key is...
このネジはですね その…
（中村(なかむら)先生）んん
A local café had been renovated, so I tried going in.
（祐子）地元の喫茶店が
リニューアルしたので 入ってみた
Um...
（玉村(たまむら)）あの…
What would you like to order?
ご注文は？
An espresso T.
エスプレッソの…
ティーで
Nichijou 64
え… えーと
So, would you like a tall espresso?
エスプレッソの
トールでよろしいでしょうか？
（祐子）
トオオッ ト… トール？
Tall?!
Tooru?!
透？
T is for tall?!
Ｔ(ティー)って トール？
Well, I feel like having a tall espresso.
いやあ エスプレッソの
ティーを飲もうかなあって
えっと じゃあ エスプレッソの
ティーのスモールで
I'll have a small-sized T. espresso, then.
エ… エスプレッソの
ショートでよろしいでしょうか？
Do you want a short espresso?
（祐子）ぐわっ　ハア ハア
うぐっ　その…
A small short is fine.
スモールのショートで―
結構です！
は… はい
All right.
Okay, an espresso...
では エスプレッソの…
Um... Hot or iced...?
ええっと
ホットとアイスがあるのですが
んっ　じゃあ ホットで！
I'll have it hot.
Um, well...
（玉村）ああ その…
For a hot...
ホットになりますと サイズが…
The sizes are...
ハア…
Solo or... doppio.
ソロとドッピオになりますが
D-Doppio?!
（祐子）
ドドド ドッピオ？ ドッピオ？
Doppio?!
What the heck is doppio?! Doppio, doppio!
ドッピオって何だ？ ななな 何だ？
ドッピオ ドッピオ？ ドッピオ？
What the heck is doppio?! What the heck?!
ドッピオって何？ 何なーの？
[All items on the menu are foreign]
Coffee of the Day
（祐子）ああっ
そ… そうだ　そうだ忘れてた
Oh, that's right. I forgot.
I think I'll get the coffee of the day.
この 本日のコーヒーにしようと
思ってたんだ
Um...
（玉村）あのっ
（祐子）ん？
（玉村）ハア ハア
Today's is espresso.
本日は エスプレッソに
なっておりますが
All right, I'll get that.
じゃあ それで
Well, then...
（玉村）はい　ですと…
Solo...
ソロと―
ハア
Or doppio?
ドッピオがございますが
（祐子）あああああ
（玉村）ドッピオが
Or doppio, doppio, doppio?
ドッピオがございますが
（祐子）
うぐっ くっくっ うう…
（祐子）で… ヘヘ ですよねえ
That makes sense...
じゃ… じゃあ―
W-Well, then...
I'll leave it up to you.
そこらへん
適当に みつくろってください
あっ 分かりました
Understood.
Sorry for the wait.
（新田(にった)）お待たせしました
エスプレッソになります
Here's your espresso.
（祐子）ちっさ
It's tiny.
And it's really bitter!
超苦(にげ)え！
Thank you for your business!
（玉村･新田）
ありがとうございました
Well, I guess...
（祐子）もう なんつーか…
...I'll just use vending machines from now on.
これからは 自販機で いいや
Joy
Happiness
Celebration
Fortune
I gave a baseball glove to my grandson, Mii-chan, for his birthday.
（教頭先生）孫の
みーちゃんの誕生日に
Catch
グローブを
プレゼントしてあげた
Grandpa! I'm throwing it!
（みーちゃん）おじき　投げるよ
Hey, Mii-chan.
（教頭）おいおい　みーちゃん
そんなに離れてちゃ届かないよ
If you stand that far away, you won't be able to throw it over here.
My grandson is really cute, being this delighted...
（教頭）
こんなに喜んでくれるなんて
やっぱり 孫はカワイイ
いっくよ
Here it comes!
All right. Throw it with all your strength.
しょうがないな
思いっきり投げるんだぞ
I should act cool for him tod-
（教頭）どれ 今日は ちょっと
カッコいいところでも見せ…
Is he a pro?
（教頭）シンカー
Agonising!!
Made On The Chef's Whim
Piping-Hot Chicken Bar
50 Yen
New
Tiko Mart
（祐子）あ… あの
（店員）はい
Um...
Yes?
I'd like one of those "Agonising!",
この 悶絶アチアチ ホットな
シェフの気まぐれチキンバーを１つ
piping hot chicken bars made on the chef's whim.
プッ フフフ
お客さん　勘弁してくださいよ
Miss, give me a break!
（長野原(ながのはら)みお）ああ
（笹原幸治郞(ささはらこうじろう)）んん？
What is it, Kojirou?
（コジロウの鳴き声）
（笹原）どうした？ コジロウ
That's right.
そうだ　急がなきゃ
受付 終わっちゃ…
I have to hurry.
They'll close-
Mio-chan!
（祐子）みーおちゃん
（みお）わあっ
Y-Yukko, what's up?
ゆ… ゆっこ　どうしたの？
Well, you disappeared right after class ended.
どうしたのって―
ホームルーム終わって
気付いたら いないんだもん
Oh, I see.
ああ そ… そっか
You don't need to be in such a hurry.
今からでも遅くはない 一緒に…
Let's go home together.
いやあ ちょっと
これから用事が
Well, sorry, I have some business to attend to.
Oh? What is it?
Uh, well, you see...
（みお）ああ えーとまあ
それと言って…
What's with that pompous style of speech?
（祐子）ええ 何？
その もったいぶった言い方
Well, how should I say it...
いやあ なんと言うか まあ
What's wrong with it?
（祐子）
いいじゃん いいじゃん
Could I have a moment?
（警官）ちょっと いいかな？
Nichijou 65
I...
I'm sorry!
すいませんでした！
Hey, Yukko!
ちょっ ゆっこ
あんた 何やったの？
What have you done?!
ハッ　なんか
つい謝っちゃったよ
I just apologised without thinking!
アッハハハ
Well, that surprised me, too.
いや 僕もビックリしたよ
いきなり謝られたから
You suddenly apologised to me.
I'm sorry.
すいません
So, what did you want?
それで 何か御用ですか？
Well, lately, there have been cases of counterfeit bills being used on vending machines.
いやねえ 最近自販機の
偽札事件が多くてね
I was just wondering if you'd seen anyone suspicious around.
怪しい人物とか
見なかったかなあと思って
Well, Mio-chan?
みおちゃん　どう？
I don't visit this area often.
ここら辺
あんまり通らないからね
According to witnesses,
目撃情報によると―
the culprit has a beige bag with red lines on it.
犯人は 赤いラインの入った
ベージュのトートバック
There's no way that cou-
…て まさか そんなわけ
What's that conspicuous reaction for?!
何？ この尋常じゃない反応
Does she have some?
持ってるの？ 偽札 持ってるの？
Does she have counterfeit bills?
No, there's no way...
いやいや まさかねえ
Man, stop joking around, Mi-
もう冗談よしてよ みお…
Why is she preparing to be handcuffed?!
なんで 自ら
お縄に かかりにいってるの？
Hey, do you have some counterfeit bills?
おいおい
持っているのか？ 偽札
ま… まさかあ
Of course not!
She's just preparing to hit a volleyball.
どこから バレーボールが
来てもいいように―
構えてるだけですよ
ねっ みおちゃん
Right, Mio-chan?
うーん まあ いいか
Well, whatever.
一応 念のために
２人ともカバンの中だけ見せて
Let me check inside your bags, just in case.
Go right ahead.
はい どーぞ
Come on, Mio-cha-
ほら みおちゃん
（祐子）イヤー！
She took it out!
出しおった 偽札 出しおった
She took out a counterfeit bill!
It's over!
終わった
まさか本当に持ってるとは
I can't believe she actually had one!
Please let me off with this.
これで 勘弁してください
Please let me off with this!
これで 勘弁してください！
Is this the only counterfeit bill you have?
これ１枚だけか？ 偽札は
偽札じゃないです
リアルな賄賂です
It's not a counterfeit!
It's a real bribe!
I don't understand what you're saying!
言ってる意味が分からん！
Just give me your bag!
とにかくカバンを！
コラッ なぜ抵抗する
Why are you resisting?!
It belongs to a relative!
親戚のだから！
このカバン 親戚のだから
It's because this bag belongs to a relative!
You're an
idiot.
Ah!
Senpai...
I...
Idiot.
（男）バカヤロウ
（みお）えいっ！
（警官）ううっ
One! Two! Three! Four! Five!
（みお）ワン ツー
スリー フォー ファイブ
Six?!
６(ろく)！
Eh?!
That's
not
true...
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
...was
one of
passion.
Passion.
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
...was
one of
passion.
...was
one of
passion.
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
（男）パッション
...was
one of
passion.
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
...was
one of
passion.
Eh?!
It seems
that
your fever
has gone
down.
That's
not
true...
The fever...
...was
one of
passion.
（祐子）キュー
（コジロウ）メエッ
Fever. Stupid. Stupid. Stupid. Stupid.
（田中(たなか)）ん？ うーん
ええっ！
何？ 何なの？ 事件？
What happened?! A crime?!
Oh, Kojirou. There you are.
（笹原）おお コジロウ
そこにおったか
（コジロウ）メエ メエ…
You look like you were just born.
（笹原）生まれたてのようだぞ
Mio!
（長野原よしの）みお
Aren't you going to eat?
ごはん食べないの？ 冷めちゃうよ
It'll get cold!
It's
pretty
obvious.
Stop
Idiot
Toshi, what is this?
Hey, Mio!
ねえ みお　ねえってば！
Hey!
Victory
Kojirou is like this
Kojirou is like this.
（笹原）フン
何を食べてるのっ！
What are you-
Well, that's all for today.
（桜井）はい　じゃあ
今日は これで終わりです
I've put up the topics for the midterm, so please go and check them.
中間試験の範囲
張り出してあるので―
各自 確認してってくださいね
Goodbye!
（なの）さよなら
Nano-chan always leaves really early.
なのちゃん いつも
いちもくさんに帰るよね
Goodbye.
（男子生徒）さよなら
（教頭）はい さよなら
（女子生徒たち）さよなら
Word Of The Day
（教頭）はい　さよなら
If I have a weakness, I think I'll pretend to know about it.
（みお）あっ ゆっこ
消しゴム借りていい？
Yukko, may I borrow an eraser?
All right.
Which one?
どっち？
Mai-chan, may I borrow an eraser?
麻衣(まい)ちゃん　消しゴム貸して
Wow!
（祐子）わおっ！
（水上(みなかみ)麻衣）分かった
Okay.
（麻衣）はい
（みお）キャラ消し！
A character eraser?!
Nichijou 66
This won't erase very well.
これじゃ消すっていうか―
伸びる一方だよ
Yukko, let me borrow an eraser.
ゆっこ　消しゴム貸して
麻衣ちゃんも なかったのか
You don't have one either, Mai-chan?
I guess I have no choice.
しょうがないなあ
はい　どっち？
All right, which one?
（みお･麻衣）こっち！
（祐子）わおっ
This one.
Wow!
No, no, no, no, no, no!
The rule is one person at a time, so that doesn't count!
ルールは１人ずつだから
今の なし！
（みお）
いつ決まったんだ？ そのルール
When did that rule get set?
All right, Mai-chan goes first.
じゃ 麻衣ちゃんから
Go ahead, look as closely as you want.
どうぞ どうぞ
ご自由にお調べくださーい
ああっ 熱っ 熱っ 熱
No, no!
なし なし ダメージ攻撃なしで！
Damaging attacks aren't allowed!
Mai-chan, you get 1-P.
麻衣ちゃん　ワンペナね
1-P?
ワンペナって？
One penalty.
ワン･ペナルティです
Does something happen if you get one penalty?
ワン･ペナルティだと
何かあるの？
You have to treat me to 23 juices!
ジュース23本おごり！
She still has a grudge about that?
（みお）
まだ 根に持ってたのか
Here, Yukko.
はい ゆっこ　ベビースター
Baby Star.
（祐子）あああっ
開いちゃう 開いちゃう
Kan ji zai bo sa tsu gyou jin han nya ha ra mit ta ji shou kei go...
TL Note: Yukko is reciting the first part of the Hart Sutra, a Zen Buddhist chant.
観自在菩薩(かんじざいぼーさー)
行深般若波羅蜜多時(ぎょうじんはんにゃはらみーたーじ) 照見五(しょうけーご)
とお！ 危なっ
開いちゃうところだったよ
That was close!
My hand was about to open!
It's "shou ken go", not "shou kei go".
“ショケーゴ”じゃなくて
“ショウケンゴ”
I thought it would work.
いけると思ったんだけどなあ
That's two penalties.
もう ツーペナもんだよ
Rock, paper, scissors.
（麻衣）じゃんけん
（祐子）ああっ
（麻衣）ぽい
甘い　さすがに
握ってるほうは出さないでしょ
How naive.
Of course I won't open the hand I'm holding it with.
（麻衣）こっち
This one.
Oh, crap!
しまったあ 謀られた
I've been played!
Well then, Yukko, give me your eraser.
それでは ゆっこ　消しゴムを
All right, all right.
Here, you win.
はい　当たり
Character erasers doing wrestling moves?!
（みお）キャラ消し 技かけ
Thank you for your business!
（店員）
ありがとうございました
The character erasers didn't work after all.
（みお）やっぱり
キャラ消しじゃ 消えないね
Right?
（祐子）だね
あっ なのちゃんだ
It's Nano-chan.
It is.
（みお）ホントだ
（なの）ううーん　ハア
Nano-chan must be a robot after all.
（祐子）なのちゃんって
やっぱりロボなんじゃ
Stop that.
いいかげんにしなよ
Nano-chan doesn't like it.
なのちゃん いやがってるよ
Huh?
ええっ？ なんでイヤなの？
すごいじゃん ロボ
Why doesn't she like it?
Robots are amazing!
Love-Like
Hey.
（女子生徒）ねえ
Let's run.
走ってこっか？
Father.
The Truth in the 15th Year
（中之条）
お父さん　ねえ お父さん
Hey, Father!
Do you really go out into town wearing this?
ホント これ かぶって
町に出るの？ 僕 恥ずかしいよ
It embarrasses me!
Embarrasses you?
（中之条さん）
恥ずかしい… だと？
You cowardly child!
この腰抜け草だんごがあ
Nichijou 67
Um... Shinonome... Shinonome...
えーと 東雲 東雲
Oh, here it is.
あっ ここだ！
Shinonome Institute...
“東雲研究所”
Wow!
へえ 研究所なんだ
カッコいい
It's an institute?
Cool!
Excuse me!
（祐子）
すいませーん　ごめんくださーい
Huh?
あれ？ 留守かなあ
Are they out?
Yes, I'm coming!
（なの）はーい　ただいま
おわっ
Sorry for making you wai-
（なの）すいません お待…
W-What should I do?!
（なの）どどど… どうしよう？
なんで相生さんが家に来てるの？
Why did Aioi-san come to my house?!
If she meets the Professor, she'll definitely find out that I'm a robot!
はかせと 鉢合わせになったら
確実にロボだってバレちゃう
Coming!
Oh, good day.
うーん どうしよう
Huh? Where's Nano-chan?
What should I do?
あっ 待てよ
But wait,
maybe she just came over to give me a printout from school.
もしかしたら プリントか何か
届けに来ただけかも
Hooray! Come in! Come in!
If that's the case, she doesn't need to-
だとしたら 玄関先で
I'm coming in.
This way.
（はかせ）どうぞ どうぞ
（祐子）あっ おかまいなく
Thank you.
（なの）アホ！
（祐子）おお
（はかせ）エヘヘ
（なの）
うう… 上がってしまったものは
しょうがない
I can't help that she came inside.
I'll just have to find out what she
wants before the Professor says any-
はかせが よけいなことを
言う前に用件を聞…
（阪本(さかもと)）ああっ 腹減っ
I'm hung-
腹減っ
（阪本）腹減っ
（祐子）おっ？
What was that voice?
That's our cat, Sakamoto.
（はかせ）
猫の阪本　しゃべるんだよ
He talks.
（なの）はかせ！
Professor!
（祐子）本当？
Really?!
Of course not!
そ… そんなわけないじゃ
ないですか
Sakamoto-san, say "meow"!
さ… 阪本さん
ニャーって言ってください
ニャーって
Why do I have to-
（阪本）ああっ？
なんで 俺が いまさ…
It's "meow", Sakamoto-san.
ニャーです 阪本さん
M-Meow.
（阪本）ニャ… ニャ～
See?
ねっ ただの猫でしょ？
Just a regular cat.
Sakamoto-san...
（なの）阪本さん
今日は お客さんが来てるから―
...we have a guest today, so go play outside, all right?
外で遊んで来てくださいね
What was that?
（阪本）なんだと？
（なの）うううっ
（阪本）怖っ
Scary!
（阪本）ハアッ　ニャア～
Meow.
I haven't introduced myself, have I?
（祐子）まだ ちゃんと
あいさつしてなかったね
I'm Aioi Yuuko.
相生祐子です
もしかして なのちゃんの妹？
Are you Nano-chan's younger sister?
No, I'm the Professor.
違います はかせです
なのを作りました
I created Nano.
（なの）だああ！
Created?!
作った？
すごい 小っこいのに すごい
Amazing!
You're so small, but amazing!
ヘへへ
はかせは はかせなので
Professor is a professor, after all.
ちち… 違いますよ 相生さん
No, Aioi-san!
She's the child of a relative of mine,
この子はですね
親戚の子どもで 親が共働きで―
and they both work and don't come home until late, so I watch over her.
夜まで帰ってこないから
それまで面倒みてるんですよ
Right?
ねっ そうだよね ねっ
Isn't that right?
What are you saying?
何 言ってんの？
Stupid!
（なの）アホッ アホ！
（祐子）へええ
I'm sorry.
（なの）すみません
お茶入れ直してきますね
I'll go make some more tea.
Oh, wait a minute, Nano.
あっ なの　ちょっと待って
If you want tea...
お茶なら ポチッ
ぎゃああっ
Go ahead.
はい どうぞ
すごい！ すごーい
Amazing! Amazing!
（はかせ）エヘッ
ギャッ イヤー！
This one is a gun.
こっちは銃です
Cool!
カッコいい　超カッコいい
Super cool!
エヘヘッ
I'm finished!
（なの）もう ダメだ
Next, we'll have a cool line competition!
じゃあ 次は
カッコいい言葉 対決！
イエーイ！
Yay!
I'll start!
（祐子）では 不肖
ゆっこから いきまーす
おい 冗談だろ　起きろよ
起きろっつってんだろう
You're just joking, right?
Wake up!
Wake up, I said!
おお カッコいい
Oh! Cool!
Your turn, Professor!
次 はかせ！
はーい！
What a pain!
カブトムシ！
Cool!
カッコいい
What did Aioi-san come here for?
（なの）いったい 相生さん
何しに来たんだろう？
They're on top of each other!
（祐子）残ってる
（はかせ）わあ ああ！
（祐子）アハハハッ
（はかせ）ギブ ギブ
I give! I give!
So small!
（祐子）もう 小さい 小さい
So big!
（はかせ）デッカい
（祐子）フウッ よし 帰る
Well, I should go.
She had no reason?!
（なの）用事なしか！
Thank you for today.
（祐子）今日は ありがとう
遅くまで ごめんね
Sorry for staying so long.
（なの）あっ いえ
It's fine.
Um, Aioi-san!
あ… あの 相生さん
Hm?
I'm actually studying magic, so, um,
（なの）
私 実は 手品の勉強中でして
決してロボとか そういうんじゃ
I'm definitely not a robot or any-
Yeah, I know.
（祐子）うん 分かってるって
なのちゃんがロボじゃないってこと
You're not a robot, Nano-chan.
よいしょっと
You're Nano-chan.
（祐子）
なのちゃんは なのちゃんだし
それで いいんじゃない？
Isn't that enough?
I came over today to say that.
今日は それを
言いに来たのだった
I'd forgotten.
忘れてたよ
Well, bye.
そんじゃ またね
（なの）あっ はい
Yeah.
Aioi-san!
（なの）相生さん！
（祐子）ん？
Um...
あのっ ああ…
If you'd like...
また よかったら…
Yeah!
おう！ 来る来る
I'll come back!
（なの）わあ
（はかせ）本当？
Really?!
（なの）えっ？
（はかせ）やった！
Hooray!
（祐子）おおっと
Let's draw pictures next time!
今度は 絵 描こうか？
Yeah! I'll draw sharks!
Sharks, huh? Those are cool!
（祐子）サメか カッコいいな
They are cool!
（はかせ）うん　カッコいいよ
I love them!
（はかせ）サメ好き
You like sharks, huh, Professor?
（祐子）はかせ　サメ好きなの？
I love sharks!
They're so cool!
（はかせ）カッコいいもん
（祐子）サメー！ サメサメ
（はかせ）きゃあ！
もっとやって もっとやって
（はかせ）
ハハハハ もっと もっと
（祐子）トリプル サメー！
（なの）ハア
（はかせ）ゆっこ　面白ーい
Professor!
（なの）はかせ　私も！
Let me join, too!
あっ 阪本だ
Oh, it's Sakamoto.
じゃあね
Bye.
（阪本）じゃあな
Well, whatever.
まあっ いっか
"Plus screw" sounds neat, doesn't it?
TL Note: "Plus" is what Japanese call Phillips-heads.
（ネジ）
プラスネジって いい響き
ポジティブな感じがします
It has a positive feeling.
It somehow makes you feel optimistic.
人生 いかなるときも前向きに！
Next episode of Nichijou is episode 17.
次回の「日常」は
第17話　お楽しみに
Narration
Look forward to it!